Tom Whipple

- mail@tomwhipple.com
- http://www.tomwhipple.com
- 612-220-1465

SUMMARY

Software engineer and entrepreneur with more than 10 years experience with a wide array of technologies, currently specializing in mobile applications. Interested in developing and applying sophisticated technologies in a startup environment.

Specialties: Technical leadership, iPhone, Android, Objective-C, Mathematics, computer vision, embedded systems

EXPERIENCE

PayPal

07 / 2012 - Present

Software Engineer/Manager

Responsible for leading a distributed team of engineers building the next generation of PayPal SDKs enabling app developers to quickly and easily accept payments.

We release directly and frequently to GitHub and communicate directly with developers on GitHub and StackOverflow. Our iOS & Android SDKs provide a drop-in way to accept PayPal & credit card payments. The server SDKs (PHP, Java, .net, Python, Ruby & node.js) provide a convenient interface to PayPal's new REST API.

Our team leads much of the developer strategy at PayPal and is responsible for driving endto-end experiences that are important to mobile developers.

card.io

07 / 2011 - 07 / 2012

Principal Software Engineer

card.io is a mobile computer vision solution that saves users the trouble of entering credit card numbers by hand. card.io was acquired by PayPal in 2012 and continues to operate as a standalone product.

As part of this small team, I served as technical lead for the Android SDK and fraud control as well as contributing to the iOS SDK and computer vision backend.

Smartovation Technologies

08 / 2009 - 07 / 2011

Founder

Smartovation Technologies was a contract software development company with expertise in mobile software.

Lead engineering for various iOS, Android & Mac OSX projects.

NAVAIR

09 / 2007 - 08 / 2009

Computer Engineer

NAVAIR is the Naval Air Systems Command, a civilian agency within the US Navy.

- Developed Hardware in the Loop (HiL) test capability for an airborne ultra-wideband digital RF receiver.
- Lead Technical Point of Contact for two SBIR technology development projects involving digital wide band RF receivers.
- Developed a maximum likelihood algorithm for classifying RF signals.
- Wrote real-time control software for custom built RF signal generation hardware for a HiL

environment.

Intel 05 / 2006 - 08 / 2006

Graduate Technical Intern

Designed and created an open source application test suite for the 1.0 release of xdg-utils. As part of the freedesktop.org Portland project, the xdg-utils are designed to provide a set of controls to providers of Linux software that work regardless of distribution or desktop environment.

Nistevo 2000 - 2003

Software Engineer

- Developed a new XML based test framework for QA.
- Undertook a variety of build automation tasks in support of product integration.
- Served as lead report developer for a Brio/Hyperion SQR reporting package and web portal.
- Administered an enterprise integration package (SeeBeyond eGate) during the go-live period. Created automated monitoring and recovery tools.

Znet Telecom 1997 - 2000

Network Administrator

Served as a lead network & system administrator for a growing WAN, including: Coordinating & supporting installation of WAN lines delivered by telecom carriers. Delivering new technologies to customers when it became available. (e.g. DSL, VoIP & WiFi).
- Maintaining servers required to run an ISP. - Custom web development. - Consulting to

customers.

EDUCATION

University of Minnesota-Twin Cities

2005 - 2007

MS , Computer Science

University of Minnesota-Twin Cities

2003 - 2005

BS, Mathematics

Solar Vehicle Project